Finding Aid for Institute of Gerontology (University of Michigan) records 1948-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Institute of Gerontology (University of Michigan) Records 1948-1987
University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.
28 linear feet
Interdisciplinary institute at the University of Michigan and Wayne State University for the study of aging. Records include administrative files relating to the activities, research, publications and conferences of the Institute's University of Michigan program; audio-visual material, and photographs.
86996 Bimu C6 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group (donor No. 6160 ) was transferred from the Institute of Gerontology Library in October 1984. Additions are expected periodically.
The collection is open for research.
Work on aging at the University of Michigan began under the auspices of the Institute for Human Adjustment. The nation's first adult education program for older people was begun in 1948 by Clark Tibbitts, then director of the institute. In 1951 the Board of Regents of the University created the Division of Gerontology as part of the Institute for Human Adjustment. Wilma Donahue, of the Psychological Clinic, was appointed the division's first chairperson. In 1965 the Michigan State Legislature passed House Bill No. 2748 to create the Institute of Gerontology (IoG), jointly sponsored by the University of Michigan and Wayne State University. Wilma Donahue and Lawrence Power were named co-directors.
In the enabling act, IoG's objectives were defined as: "developing new and improved programs for helping older people in [Michigan], for the training of persons skilled in working with the problems of the aged, for research related to the needs...of our aging population, and for conducting community service programs in the field of aging." To accomplish these objectives, the institute has worked closely with other units of the universities. The IoG offers short courses for in-service training, a curricula at the master's level, and seeks to attract doctoral students in several disciplines to specialize in gerontological problems.
At the outset, Wayne State and the University of Michigan took responsibility for different aspects of the institute's unitary plan. Wayne State emphasized medical and health related fields, while the University of Michigan concentrated on economic, social, employment/retirement, and educational areas. The University of Michigan's program is highlighted by several projects, among them the investigation of "milieu" therapy in the rehabilitation of geriatric mental hospital patients, the development of discussion programs for use in training community leaders to serve older persons, and stimulating the inclusion of gerontological content in the basic science and professional school curricula.
While the Institute of Gerontology has made many contributions to the nation's attitudes toward and programs for the elderly, its most visible program has been the series of annual conferences on aging which began in 1948 and ended in 1975. The conferences drew national audiences of 600 to 1300 persons who participated in workshops and listened to leading gerontologists present their most recent research findings. Many of the papers presented were published in the IoG's Occasional Papers series.
The IoG underwent considerable change in the early 1980s, beginning with the appointment of Richard Adelman as the UM co-director. Adelman shifted the IoG's focus from pedagogy and generally public-oriented programming to research. Conference activity was curtailed sharply and the continuing education program in geriatric education was rapidly phased out. The institute began to direct its attentions increasingly to multi-disciplinary research and formed alliances with a broad cross-section of UM departments, from architecture and music to medicine and biology. This approach proved difficult for some staff members, but ultimately resulted in the IoG being much more focused on research, preserving the institute's place on the leading edge of geriatric research.
The Institute of Gerontology is governed by a ten-member Executive Board. The board's members are appointed by the presidents of the two universities; in turn the board appoints the institute's co-directors. The size and composition of the institute has varied over time, depending as much on "soft" funds from individual grants as on the "hard" money provided by the parent universities. The two principle funding agencies have been the U.S. Administration on Aging and the Michigan Commission on Aging.
Co-Directors of the Institute of Gerontology
University of Michigan
1965-1969 Wilma Donahue
1969-1972 Woodrow Hunter
1972-1975 Wayne Vasey
1975-1982 Harold Johnson
1982 (acting) John E. Tropman
1982- Richard Adelman
Wayne State University
1965-1972 Lawrence Power
1973- Charles Parrish
Because of the varied sources and the original poor order of the institute's records, the arrangement is essentially artificial. The records have been arranged into nineteen series:
General Documents
Ad Hoc University Committee on Gerontology
Budget Requests and Supporting Documents
Correspondence and Memos
Annual Conferences on Aging
Conferences and Symposia
Programs, Projects, Studies, and Curricula
Unfunded Programs, Projects, Studies, and Curricula
Ann Arbor Veterans Administration Hospital
Miscellaneous
Executive Board
Executive Committee
Photographs
Publications
Multi-Media Kits
Sound Recordings.
Films; Slides
Institute Files
University Files
The Institute files have been received in several accessions, with continuations of records series in multiple accessions. The records have not been physically interfiled. The contents list of this finding aid describes the intellectual arrangement of the records, without regard to date of accessioning. The Summary contents list below provides an overview of the physical arrangement of the records.
Summary Contents List
General Documents [box 1, 12]
Ad Hoc University Committee on Gerontology, 1965 [box 1]
Executive Board Minutes, 1965-1984 [boxes 1, 12-13]
Budget Requests and Supporting Documents, 1965-1985 [boxes 1, 12]
Correspondence and Memos, 1949-1985 [boxes 1-2, 13-14]
Annual Conference on Aging, 1948-1975 [boxes 2-4, 14-15]
Publications [box 2]
Correspondence, Financial Information, Notes, Summaries, and Miscellaneous [boxes 2-3]
Addresses and Unpublished Papers [boxes 3-4]
Other Conferences and Symposia, 1942-1984 [boxes 4-5, 15, 27]
Sponsored by IoG [box 4]
Programs, Projects, Studies, Curricula, 1964-1984 [boxes 5-8, 15-17]
Biology of Aging [box 5]
Educational Gerontology Graduate Program [box 5]
Health Advocacy for Older People, Jackson County [boxes 5-6]
Milieu Therapy Training Program [boxes 6-7, 16]
"Senior Sounds": Series of Radio Programs for WUOM [box 7]
Unfunded Programs, Projects, Studies, Curricula, 1964-1971 [boxes 8-9]
Ann Arbor Veteran's Administration (AAVA) Hospital, 1976-1981 [boxes 8-9, 27]
Miscellaneous, 1956-1985 [boxes 9-10, 20]
IoG [box 9]
Gerontology [box 9]
Aging and the Elderly [boxes 9-10]
Institute Files [boxes 26-27]
University Files [box 28]
Photographs [boxes 10, 20, 27]
Sound Tapes [box 11, 23-24]
Publications, 1967-1984 [boxes 17-20, 29]
Multimedia Kits [boxes 21-22]
Films, slides [box 25]
The records of the Institute of Gerontology cover the period 1948 to 1987. They are composed of the office files of several staff members at the University of Michigan. (Not included are the records of that part of the IoG housed at Wayne State University.) Included are the scattered files of four of the institute's co-directors, the chairman of the Executive Board, the editor of the Occasional Papers series, the annual conference coordinators, and the directors of certain projects. Also included are correspondence and memos, financial information, grant proposals and reports, minutes, and printed matter. The programs for the Annual Conferences on Aging provide a "who's who" for many of the individuals represented in the collection.
The records provide an overview of the activities, policies, and personnel of the IoG from its inception. Some substantive and seminal memos and reports exist which throw light on the development of programs and on the value of certain projects. Most of the documents are routine, however, and serve primarily to introduce the researcher to the various units and activities of the institute. For details and insights into particular aspects of the IoG, the researcher should consult the separate collections of the various co-directors, directors of research, and project directors, as well as the institute's publications.
Subjects:
Aged.; Aging.; Gerontology.; Retirement.; University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Conference on Aging.; Sontag, Susan, 1933-2004; University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.
Subjects - Sound recordings
University of Michigan. Institute of Gerontology.; Aging.; Gerontology.
Contributors:
Donahue, Wilma T. (Wilma Thompson), 1900-; Hunter, Woodrow Wilson, 1913-; Johnson, Harold R.; Vasey, Wayne.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- General Documents
  The General Documents series includes a variety historical and administrative files documenting the founding, administration and programs of the Institute of gerontology. Among the most important folders in the series is that containing Program Descriptions and Progress Reports. Here are several early statements of purpose for the IoG, definitions of the division of labor between the two universities, descriptions of the duties of the executive board, and early accounts of activities. (Other progress reports will be found in the Budget Requests and Supporting Documents series.) This folder, along with those of the Ad Hoc Committee and the earliest correspondence, give a good documentation of the origins of the institute. The Promotional and Informational Material folders--course and program descriptions, mostly--give an overview of some of the training programs, both short and long-term, of the IoG.
  - Program Descriptions and Progress Reports (Box 1)
  - Promotional and Informational Material, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan Collegiate Gerontology Newsletter, 1970-71 (Box 1)
  - Agreements and By-laws (Box 12)
  - Description of IoG (Box 12)
  - Development Office (Box 12)
  - Gifts (Box 12)
  - History-"Archives" (Box 12)
  - History-General, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - History-Search for New Director 1981-1982 (Box 12)
  - History-Sponsored Projects (Box 12)
  - Organization Charts 1971-1983 (Box 12)
  - Personnel (Box 12)
  - Personnel Administration 1982 (Box 12)
  - Promotional-Informational Material 1974 (Box 12)
  - Wayne State University. Institute of Gerontology
    - Information on Aging, nos. 14-29 1977-1983 (Box 12)
    - Library Notes and News v. 2, no. 6-v.4, no. 11 September 1980-November 1981 (Box 12)
- Ad-Hoc University Committee on Gerontology 1965
  The Ad Hoc University Committee on Gerontology, 1965, was the committee responsible for implementing Governor Romney's intention to create an Institute of Gerontology. Its major task was to decide whether the proposed institute should offer a degree-granting program at the master's level, a point about which there was some considerable disagreement. The report, some of the minutes, and some of the correspondence pertain to this debate.
  - Report (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
- Annual Reports
  - 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - 1986-1988 (Box 1)
- Budget Requests and Supporting Documents 1965-1985
  By far the most informative documents in the Budget Requests and Supporting Documents, 1965-1985, series are the supporting documents--yearly "Statements of Program." These generally summarize the current status of the training, service, and research programs, as well as provide projections into the next fiscal year to justify the requested budget. Other documents include memos and correspondence--mostly routine, but occasionally discussing the justification for various components of the budget. Additional correspondence relating to budgetary and fiscal matters is found in the Correspondence series.
  - 1965-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1980-1982 (Box 12)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 12)
- Bulletins
  - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
- Correspondence and Memos 1949-1983
  The arrangement of the Correspondence and Memos, 1949-1983 series reflects the original order of the material. The series includes carbons and photocopies of correspondence sent, as well as correspondence received. There is some duplication between the files of persons in communication with one another.
  Much of the correspondence is routine, relating to the fine tuning of the budget, contacts from colleagues and friends, and personnel problems. But there is policy discussion represented as well, such as memos outlining the 1965 staff comments on the goals of the short-term training program and suggestions in 1972 for reshaping or scrapping the annual conferences. Overall, this series provides a good glimpse into both the bureaucratic and substantive concerns of the institute, as seen through the eyes of its executives.
  - 1949-1964 General (Box 1)
  - 1965-1969 Wilma Donahue, Co-Director
    - General (Box 1)
    - Stephen H. Spurr, Dean of Graduate Studies, University of Michigan (Box 1)
    - Gordon Scott, Vice-President, Wayne State University (Box 1)
    - Suggestions from IoG Faculty about Program (Box 1)
  - 1965-1969 Stephen H. Spurr, Dean of Graduate Studies, University of Michigan (Box 1)
  - 1969-1971 Wilbur J. Cohen, Chairman of IoG Executive Board (Box 1)
  - 1969-1971 Woodrow Hunter, Co-Director
    - General (Box 1)
    - Wilbur J. Cohen, Chairman of IoG Executive Board (Box 1)
    - Individual IoG Faculty and Staff (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (arranged alphabetically) (Box 1)
  - 1969-1974 Wayne Vasey, Co-Director (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Memos (Box 2)
  - 1974 Search for Vasey's Replacement
    - Internal Memos and Correspondence with Prime Candidates (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with other Candidates (Box 2)
    - Negative Responses from Solicited Applicants (Box 2)
    - Responses from Ads (Box 2)
  - 1971-1979 Miscellaneous Memos to Staff (Box 2)
  - 1975-1979 Harold Johnson, Co-Director (Box 2)
  - 1977-1979 Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - 1979 general, 6 folders (Box 13)
  - 1980 general, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - 1981 general, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - 1982 general (Box 13)
  - 1976-1981 Harold Johnson, Co-Director, 9 folders (Box 14)
  - 1982 John Tropman, Acting Co-Director, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - 1982-1983 Richard Adelman, Co-Director, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - IoG Faculty and Staff [Personnel Relations], 2 folders (Box 14)
- Annual Conferences on Aging 1948-1975
  The 1948 Annual Conference on Aging was the only meeting of its kind in the nation. Originally the conferences were primarily a means of bringing together and publishing noteworthy papers in the field of gerontology. Over time they became somewhat less academic and more "action-practitioner" oriented, with more emphasis placed on workshops and discussions. The papers and proceedings from several of the conferences were published, and may be consulted at the IoG Library (Learning Resource Center). A list of such publications will be found here in the Learning Resource Center folders of the Miscellaneous series. The Annual Conference on Aging, 1948-1975, series contains the printed programs from every conference, scattered pamphlets and rosters. More important are the Correspondence, Financial Information, Notes, Summaries, and Miscellaneous folders for scattered years. Most of these folders are from Woodrow Hunter's files. (Hunter was, at different times, conference coordinator and co-director of the institute.) Noteworthy material in the folders includes a primer for workgroup leaders (1954); descriptions of duties of workshop moderators and resource people, a survey of participants, and post-conference critiques (1973). The Conference Addresses and Unpublished Papers folders contain some transcripts of a panel discussion (1970). (See also the Sound Tapes series in this collection).
  - Publications
    - Programs, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Brochures and Pamphlets (Box 2)
    - Rosters, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Financial Information, Notes, Summaries, Miscellaneous
    - 1951 #4 (Box 2)
    - 1955 #8 (Box 2)
    - 1958 #12 (Box 2)
    - 1961 #14 (Box 2)
    - 1962 #15 (Box 2)
    - 1963 #16 (Box 2)
    - 1965 #17 (Box 2)
    - 1966 #18 (Box 2)
    - 1967 #20 (Box 2)
    - 1968 #21 (Box 2)
    - 1969 #22 (Box 2)
    - 1970 #23 (Box 2)
    - 1971 #24 (Box 3)
    - 1972 #25
      - General (Box 3)
      - American Pioneers in Aging-Nominations (Box 3)
      - American Pioneers in Aging-Biographical Information on Honorees (Box 3)
    - 1973 #26
      - Memos and Documents (Box 3)
      - General Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Correspondence with Workshop Moderators and Resource People (Box 3)
      - Conference Report and Survey Findings (Box 3)
      - Publicity (Box 3)
      - Post Conference Critiques and Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - 1974 #27
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Documents (Box 3)
    - 1975 #28
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Documents (Box 3)
      - Notes: Meetings and Telephone Conversations (Box 3)
      - Biographical Information on Speakers (Box 3)
  - Citations for Distinguished Leadership in Social Gerontology 1958-1965 (Box 3)
  - Addresses and Unpublished Papers (includes correspondence with editor)
    - 1962 #15 (Box 3)
    - 1965 #18 (Box 3)
    - 1968 #21 (Box 3)
    - 1970 #23: Transcripts
      - Panel Discussions (Box 3)
      - Introductions and Addresses (Box 3)
    - 1971 #24 (Box 3)
    - 1972 #25
      - Paper (Box 3)
      - Cassette Tape: Forum Discussion and Address by Wilma Donahue (Box 3)
      - General Correspondence re Editing and Publishing (Box 3)
      - Correspondence and Notes re Disputed Paper (Box 3)
      - Excerpts, Introductions, and a French Manuscript (Box 3)
  - 1973 #26 (Box 4)
    - 1974 #27 (Box 4)
    - 1975 #28: Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Undated and Miscellaneous Addresses and Papers (Box 4)
  - 4th-11th 1951-1958 (Box 14)
  - 12th-17th 1959-1964 (Box 14)
  - 18th-23rd 1965-1970 (Box 14)
  - 24th-26th 1971-1973 (Box 15)
  - 26th, "Women: Life Span Challenges" 1973 (Box 15)
  - 27th 1974 (Box 15)
- Other Conferences, Symposia, Colloquia, Seminars, Forums 1949-1984
  The Other Conferences and Symposia, 1950-1980 series documents conferences sponsored by IoG as well as some which IoG staff participated in. The most important portions of this series are those conferences sponsored by the IoG. The Aging and the Art of Living conference spawned an exhibit of Images of Old Age in America, sponsored by the Smithsonian Institute, which toured the country from 1977 through 1986. The Issues in Aging Training Workshop brought state government officials from across the nation together to exchange ideas and information and to receive guidance from the academic community.
  - Sponsored by IoG
    - Workshop on Older Americans Act 1966 (Box 4)
    - Social Services Workshop 1966 (Box 4)
    - Institute on Aging (co-sponsor) 1967 (Box 4)
    - Research Symposium on Spatial Behavioral Relationships as Related to Older People (Box 4)
    - Faculty Seminars in Social Gerontology 1968-1971 (Box 4)
    - Humanistics of Terminal Care 1969 (Box 4)
    - Protecting the Elderly-Intervention Workshops 1971 (Box 4)
    - Issues in Aging Training Workshops 1971
      - Proposal and Progress Reports (Box 4)
      - Planning (Box 4)
      - Introductory Letters (Box 4)
      - Rosters and Schedules (Box 4)
      - Financial Information (Box 4)
    - Biology of Aging 1975
      - Blood Pressure Control Conference 1975 (Box 4)
      - Aging and the Art of Living 1977
        - Grant Proposals (Box 4)
        - Correspondence, Memos, Programs, Budgets, etc (Box 4)
        - Images of Old Age in America (Box 4)
      - Higher Education and the Aging Colloquium 1978
        - Correspondence and Documents (Box 4)
        - Papers (Box 4)
      - Creativity and Aging Lecture and Performance Series 1980 (Box 4)
  - Attended by Woodrow Hunter, Co-Director
    - National Conference on Aging (Washington, D.C.) 1950 (Box 4)
    - Second International Gerontological Congress (St. Louis) 1951 (Box 4)
    - Governor's Michigan Conference on Aging (East Lansing) 1952 (Box 4)
    - White House Conference on Aging (Washington, D.C.) 1971
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Education Subsection (Box 4)
      - Plans and Procedures (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Mimeographed Documents (Box 4)
      - Booklets, Publications, Programs (Box 4)
  - Attended by Wilma Donahue, Co-Director: Eighth International Gerontological Congress (Washington, D.C.) 1969 (Box 5)
    - General Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Correspondence re: Luncheon Program (Box 5)
    - Addresses and Papers (Box 5)
    - Correspondence re: Visiting IoG (Box 5)
  - Aging and Social Health in the United States and Europe, International Seminar, Merano, Italy July 9-13, 1957 (Box 15)
  - Alumni University, 11th 1949 (Box 15)
  - Colloquium "Future roles of higher education in the field of aging" 1978 (Box 15)
  - Colloquium "Higher education and aging: a look to the future" 1978 (Box 15)
  - Conference on Aging 1975 "The economics of aging: Toward 2001" (Box 15)
  - Conference 1977 "Aging and the art of living" (Symposium, Conference, Festival), October 10-15, 1977 (Box 15)
  - Consultation-Conference on the Gerontological Aspects of Mental Retardation April 8-10, 1975 (Box 15)
  - Institute on Aging March 13-14, 1967 (Box 15)
  - Older Worker Conference 1981
    - Proposal, budget, progress report (Box 15)
    - Final report (Box 15)
  - Programs, miscellaneous 1975 (Box 15)
  - Seminar "Preretirement education" 1979, 1981 (Box 15)
  - Seminars in Social Gerontology for Faculty of Michigan Educational Institutions (Box 15)
  - Statewide Policy Conference on the Older Worker March 1981 (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan, Biomedical Research Council Forum March 10, 1984 (Box 15)
- Programs, Projects, Studies, Curricula 1942-1984
  The Programs, Projects, Studies, and Curricula, 1964-1981, series provides some of the best documentation of the variety of the IoG's programmatic work. The best documented of those programs also seem to be among the most important. The Biology of Aging program--of which the 1975 conference was but an early stage--documents the lengthy development of a proposal to initiate an interdisciplinary Ph.D. program in research on the physiology of the aging process. Material on the Educational Gerontology Graduate program includes proposals, memos, and correspondence relating to the origins of the nation's first curricula to bestow advanced degrees for teaching the elderly. The program was developed under the aegis of the School of Education, with interdisciplinary support.
  The Health Advocacy for Older People project served Oakland, Livingston, Washtenaw, and Jackson counties, though the material in this collection is from Jackson County only. The project sought to improve access to and the quality of health care for low-income older people by training peer advocates and holding informational workshops. The Milieu Therapy Training program was a long-term research and demonstration project to improve the environment and hence the treatment of elderly mental patients.